

LINUX SYSTEMS ENGINEER DEVOPS ENGINEER

SUMMARY

10+ years of experience in Linux systems administration in the fields of web hosting and cloud services, results-driven with diverse information technology experience emphasizing cross-platform systems and network architecture. A passionate technologist with a strong desire for personal growth. Automation enthusiast with strong scripting skills. Skilled problem identifier, troubleshooter, comfortable managing systems, projects and teams in a range of IT environments.

CORE COMPETENCIES

- **Linux Administration and Troubleshooting:** Demonstrated solid skill in configuring and managing Linux servers for various services such as: Web, Databases, Email, File Servers, etc. Keen eye for troubleshooting and extensive knowledge of how systems work including networking, DNS, Databases and Email.
- **Designing Technical Architecture:** Designed systems to satisfy customer requirements on top of well-known open source stacks and cloud service providers. Advised on best recommended architectures for performance, agility and cost-optimization. Helped customers create, maintain and operate stacks on different platforms.
- Advanced knowledge of Web Hosting: Worked extensively with web hosting stacks on Linux, including: Apache, NGINX, MySQL, cPanel, Plesk and CloudLinux. Demonstrated deep understanding of optimizing services for performance and security. Helped customers troubleshoot and resolve common and advanced issues..
- **Cybersecurity:** Well-rounded knowledge of information security, with emphasis on web applications, common attack vectors, mitigation methods, WAF and ModSecurity configuration, applications and server hardening, and incident investigation. Proficient in identifying and cleaning infected CRMs including; Wordpress, Joomla and Drupal.
- **Configuration Management:** Written and maintained Ansible Playbooks to automate server configuration, well versed with Terraform and Packer for provisioning cloud resources. An advocate for Infrastructure-as-Code practices. Helped development teams to design and implement CI/CD pipelines using Jenkins, GitLab CI/CD and Github Actions.
- **Monitoring and Logging:** Designed and implemented monitoring and logging infrastructure for multiple projects, small and large. Solid experience with Prometheus, Grafana, and Zabbix for monitoring, Graylog for log aggregation, enrichment and analysis, and AlertManager and OpeGenie for alerting and escalation.
- **Docker and Kubernetes:** Proficient use of Docker for building and deploying containerized applications, written Dockerfiles and maintained docker images for various applications. Built and deployed applications at scale using Docker Swarm and Kubernetes. Provided technical expertise in troubleshooting and optimizing docker images.
- **Programming and Scripting:** Proficient in developing with Python programming language to create tools to improve teams workflow including: custom dashboards, automation scripts, command-line tools, and GUI utilities. Working knowledge of Bash scripting language for quick-hacks and one-off scripts.
- **Technical Writing:** Does not shy from writing in technical subjects with proficiency, maintains organized and accurate documentation, shares technical knowledge in terms of How-To and Troubleshooting articles regularly. Well versed in proper electronic documents formatting. Working knowledge of using LaTeX and Markdown.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Libyan Spider Ltd. Remote

SENIOR SYSTEMS ENGINEER | TECHNICAL MANAGER | CTO

Feb. 2016 - Present

Libyan Spider, established in 2002 has grown into a world-class web hosting provider. Offering technical solutions around web technologies, including: web hosting, dedicated servers, VPS, cloud solutions, and Web and Mobile development.

- Managed a large infrastructure containing hundreds of physical and virtual servers
- · Automated provisioning and deployment using Ansible AWX and Terraform to minimize human errors and to reduce deployment times
- Deployed and managed logging infrastructure with Graylog for organization-wide log ingestion and data analysis to find trends related to performance, security, and user behavior.
- Packaged Docker machines for the development team micro services projects
- Performed Level 3 Support duties to troubleshoot complex problems and devised solutions for bottlenecks and other issues
- · Managed multiple teams including: Technical Support, Infrastructure, Kaspersky Technical Support, and Development Team
- Implemented a monitoring solution based on Zabbix, the solution focused on deep monitoring for hardware, network, and services health
- · Developed tools to automate repetitive tasks for the support team and to improve tickets response time
- Assisted clients in the design and implementation of technical solutions
- Managed multiple development projects including Mobile App projects and Web Application projects
- Led the organization project successfully to implement ISO27001 and ISO27017
- Led infrastructure projects successfully to implement IaaS and PaaS platforms

LibyaOnLine.comTripoli, Libya

Technical Manager Nov. 2012 - Feb. 2016

Founded in 1998, LOL is one of the first Libyan companies specialized in web hosting and development. I've been hired to manage the company line of web products and services, refocusing the company's direction and priorities. I have been working on web development projects as well as technical solutions related to online services.

- Developing business plans for the web hosting and design business
- Developed a signature based solution for detecting malicious web content and signs of compromise
- Expanded physical and virtual hosting infrastructure
- Organized system updates, patches and maintenance schedules
- Implemented WHMCS as the main company billing and automation system
- Analyzed malware and virus samples and wrote ModSecurity filtering rules
- Trained newly hired first line technical support staff
- · Designed and implemented highly available multi-site web hosting for high profile web applications
- · Developed the company Network Operations Center, including monitoring, response and escalation procedures

Chevron Libya Ltd.

Tripoli, Libya

IT COORDINATOR Jan. 2009 - Nov. 2012

Chevron Corporation (NYSE: CVX) is an American multinational corporation, one of the world's six "super-major" oil companies.

- · Acting as the local IT support for the company Libya presence, this includes staff in HQ as well as remote drilling locations
- · Maintained security of voice and data networks and equipment. Monitored and maintained physical and logical security and access to systems
- · Assisted with testing of installed systems to ensure protection strategies are properly implemented and working as intended
- Organized security awareness training to educate employees regularly on security threats and corporate information technology use policies
- Manages Data Backup Solution, archiving, and scheduled maintenance
- Designed and implemented IT infrastructure for remote drilling locations
- Working with operations and management teams to ensure regulations and policies are implemented according to company standards and policies

LibyaOnLine.com Tripoli, Libya

Systems Enginer Dec. 2004 - Jan. 2009

Started as a Junior Engineer and been promoted several times to the position of Senior Systems Specialist

- Managed cPanel Shared and Dedicated Hosting Servers
- Bind DNS and Apache HTTP administration
- Troubleshooting System and Network related issues
- Ethernet networks installation, wiring, patching and basic network devices configuration
- Planning and configuration for Cisco Firewall rules
- Installation and configuration for Windows Active Directory ,Exchange, and Microsoft ISA
- · Support for development team through systems preparation, installation and configuration in development and production environments

EDUCATION

Atilim University Ankara, Turkey

M.Sc., Master of Science in Computer Engineering

2022 - Present

· A master's student at the School on Natural and Applied Sciences, Computer Engineering Department

University of TripoliTripoli, LibyaB.Sc., Electronics Engineering1999 - 2005

- Majored in Control and Automation
- Graduation Thesis Title: "GeoSmart Alarm Monitoring for Mobile Base Transceiver Stations"

JANUARY 27, 2023 AHMED SHIBANI · RÉSUMÉ